[SPEAKER_04]: Bhante Pasupala was speaking a lot about Yoniso Manasikāra through the concurrent attention.
[SPEAKER_04]: To me, it seems like there are a few ways that you can talk about it, to kind of bridge into the subject, peripheral awareness and being one.
[SPEAKER_04]: I know they point to the same thing, but they
[SPEAKER_04]: When I hear peripheral, it turns into tranquil music.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you could speak more about the definition of concurrent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, well, the... the yoniso, yoniso means about, it's like, it's, it's the...
[SPEAKER_02]: The most important factor that, in a sense, that a practitioner can develop that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not something like, eh... you don't need the right view in order to understand it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a prerequisite for the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can a practitioner do that?
[SPEAKER_02]: What does he need to do that he's not doing, which would make him gain that factor?
[SPEAKER_02]: Two factors for arising of the right view, yoniso manasikāra and right instruction, absence of another.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, correct, correct information.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, you could argue that, you know, there is the correct information, you know, you could find it, but it's still not, it's still won't result in the right view for as long as that, how I call it, concurrent attention or yoniso manasikāra is not developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: What is that thing that a Bhutujana could start doing, that he's not doing, that can aid and eventually result in Yadusūna-sikāra?
[SPEAKER_02]: Restraining his actions?
[SPEAKER_03]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_03]: Restraining his actions?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would be the starting point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, obviously, look further for his intentions, beyond his actions and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But all of that supports
[SPEAKER_02]: Your experience as a whole?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anything that surprises you?
[SPEAKER_02]: Anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Physical, mental, emotional, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, your attitude towards any manifested phenomenon, how would you describe that attitude?
[SPEAKER_01]: What idea would you have, in terms of what you think it is?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, attitude towards any arising dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: What kind of attitude towards any arising dhamma is necessary, as one of the factors for the right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason by itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, seeing it, inducing the present manifested to its own extent, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's like what in philosophy was kind of referred to as phenomena in phenomenology.
[SPEAKER_02]: Recognizing things as phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, see, like, when an untrained mind would have thoughts, say, about pleasant or unpleasant things, experiences, memories, future plans, they're not seen as phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: They might not necessarily deny the existence of their thoughts, but they don't see them in the right place.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, usually, it would be seen against like a backdrop of a view that all thoughts are in my head.
[SPEAKER_02]: They exist secondary to this material world that's the real measure of existence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Same with one's feelings, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intentions are generally like, oh, there's just some movement of some energies and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the real reality is, you know, the measurable
[SPEAKER_02]: The world of science and so on, the palpable stuff that we can access through the senses, that's what's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of this is sort of secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, here you are, having sleepless nights on account of your not real thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't have the material aspects to them, yet they're equally real.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the realization that whatever is manifested, to whatever extent, on any, to whatever level, so to speak, is real as such, to that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: It exists on its own, regardless of you and your perception of the world.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that, I mean, I don't mean like it exists after me or before me, because that would be, again, that external perception of the world independent of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: A present, presently enduring feelings, for example, presently enduring thoughts or a mood, it's real as such in its own domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if it's not real as such, if it's not perceived, how do you know what mood you're in?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you know what thoughts you have?
[SPEAKER_02]: You are perceiving it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just that, obviously, through non-restraint, pursuit of sensuality, development of all the wrong views towards... on the basis of perverted order of sense organs and sense bases... sorry, sense objects and sense bases, you sort of... you dismiss this.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just see past it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You see past these phenomena that are very real, and actually, they're kind of even more real than the world you assume is real.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're the closest to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the authenticity we often talk about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will lead to the mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, so that's, that's really the attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize, yeah, a person can develop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you need some instruction for it, obviously.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eh, you need sense of shame.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you need to start just practicing seeing things on their own level, to the extent that they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what Buddha meant in the suttas when he says, whatever form there is, past, future, present, big, small, far, near, subtle, coarse, whatever feeling, same, past, future, present, up, down, left, in any form, any shape, any extent, he knows to the extent as it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that means that his view of recognizing things for the way they arisen is unshakable.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's established.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he cannot not see things as phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: But saying, oh, eh... Yonison Manasikāra is seeing things as phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: Joe, somebody who is familiar with phenomenology, can know what that means, but most people are not familiar with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, they will just study phenomenology without Yonison Manasikāra, without that authenticity, get a degree in phenomenology and interstitial philosophy and so on, and think they understood it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not about, like, yes, as I said, there is a degree of information you need, but then you need to start doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like phenomenology, it's not a philosophy.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an attitude of, kind of, initially, how the person who founded it, well, that he's considered as a founder, Edmund Husserl, he said, he described it as stepping back.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Putting the world in the brackets, putting your experience in the brackets.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, you step from whatever is currently absorbing you, you unabsorb yourself from it to gain perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that, he didn't, I mean, he took it
[SPEAKER_02]: In his own way, like, he'd drawn some accurate conclusions, but then kind of fell into views and started interpreting it again with these kind of external, secondary, presupposed notions.
[SPEAKER_02]: But certain people recognize the value of, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever views you might have, actually put that aside and just constantly unabsorb yourself from wherever your attention is becoming absorbed.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly what yoniso manasikāra means.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means attending to whatever you're attending, but with the perspective of the source, of the womb, of the origin.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't attend the origin, because that becomes the object of your attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's why I was saying, the reason...
[SPEAKER_02]: I know it's not scholastically accurate when I say concurrent attention, but dhamma is not a scholastic thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're studying dhamma scholastically, you are not studying the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: I call it concurrent attention because it reveals that concurrent to what?
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Concurrent to what?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, concurrent to yourself being unabsorbed from whatever is trying to absorb you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And your attention is always going to be resting on something.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that does not mean that you always need to be absorbed, unaware of yourself in regard to whatever your attention is resting on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the beginning of yonisamādhisikāra is kind of the beginning of that phenomenology, the beginning of stepping back, unabsorbing yourself, in order to simultaneously have a perspective and you're there with whatever you're attending.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it could prevent you from going too far down the rabbit hole of absorbed sense that wants to pull you and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the Buddha exactly said that.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no single thing that brings desire to increase
[SPEAKER_02]: Un-arisen desire to arise and arisen desire to increase, such as ayoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attending to it without that source, not with a concurrent intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, there is not a single thing that brings the arisen desire to decrease and non-arisen to not arise, such as yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when one is attending from the origin, or when one is attending concurrently... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's go like this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, with the knowledge of the origin, with the knowledge of the womb.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, with the knowledge of the situation, simultaneously present with whatever you're attending as an object of that, within that situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, why does unawisened sensual desire not arise and awisened desire cease?
[SPEAKER_01]: Go on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I'm putting the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Huh?
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody else can answer it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when one is overlooking or not attending from the origin,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is basically one direction, moving that way, basically lost.
[SPEAKER_01]: One is recollecting that origin.
[SPEAKER_01]: This doesn't mean that the other direction disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's now concurrent attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is that sensual desire that isn't there not going to rise that way?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it was there, it's going to diminish.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_04]: My thought is, if you kind of put yourself out in there with the things, you can almost just snowball with it and, um...
[SPEAKER_04]: With the involvement, you get caught up in something that you don't necessarily have to be caught up in.
[SPEAKER_04]: Saying it out loud, that now sounds like a shaky response.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is like in broad strokes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It does pull you in, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was going to say, like, with perspective of something pressuring you, you realize it's pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that whole pressuring aspect of it won't be seen if you tend to ayoniso.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you are established in yoniso,
[SPEAKER_03]: The pressure will be felt as pressure, versus ayoniso.
[SPEAKER_02]: By being established in yoniso, you are already... you already stepped... you're already... you bracket the pressure as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's another thing that's arisen, which you see as...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you might not know that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might not know... you might not see the implications of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But by practicing yoniso manasikāra correctly, you are also stepping back, as I described, from the pressure, which
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, you're pulled by the pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you don't have perspective in regard to the pressure, one thing will pressure you to the next thing, to the next thing, because you're trying to outrun the pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're always hooked.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that first step, like, you step into it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you won't step into it with yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even with the arisen pressure, you will become depressurized because you cease to provide food for it, the fuel for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly why.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, as I said, you might not necessarily understand the implications of it immediately, but if you stick to it, and that's why Gautujana, an outsider, can free himself from centrality.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: If he's authentic enough, he would eventually then see through, and see the nature of centrality as pressuring, and unpleasant, and a dart, and a boil, and a debt, and everything else that would have described it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And recognize, all I need to do is maintain this concurrent intention in regard to this perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: All I need to do is not ignore, not ignore the fact what has arisen right in front of me to the extent that it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then the sensuality would eventually completely lose the appeal.
[SPEAKER_02]: But here's another question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, before we go on, I must know it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why sensuality is inherent in sāṃbhāva also.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not because of its sense objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because it requires lack of perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: It requires ayoniso.
[SPEAKER_02]: It requires entering upon that course of pressure, willingly, through ignoring.
[SPEAKER_02]: Each time you ignore, means to that extent, you don't see that thing as a phenomenon, whatever you ignored.
[SPEAKER_02]: To that extent, there is ayoniso.
[SPEAKER_02]: To that extent, you have not seen the thing arisen to the extent that it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why ignorance is the most blameworthy root of all problems.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was actually going to ask something along those lines.
[SPEAKER_01]: The desire for sensual pleasure, or for sensuality, is concerned with particular things, so to speak, and their signs and features.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is it possible that when one is attending from the origin, which is to attend to the totality of this vision experience, that, can, can that, can that mode of attention, can then at the same time dwell on signs and features of particular things?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean by dwelling then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, like, you can only... Like, pick them up or grab them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so, if you're concerned with beautiful or ugly of particular phenomena, like phenomena within phenomena, and because that's how you get absorbed and how you lose that origin.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to be drawn that way is to already not attend from the origin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, when one is attending from the origin,
[SPEAKER_01]: That whole domain is still there, but can you then pick up those signs and features and get lost in that direction while concurrently attending?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, when attending from the origin, the whole thing begins to cool down, because you keep dwelling on the totality, so to speak, and not lose yourself within it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And losing yourself within it is the fuel for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but then the key thing is to not own that origin.
[SPEAKER_01]: And say... Yeah, eventually, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can't... See, if you try to sort of, right away, start not owning it and so on, you would be attending to that without...
[SPEAKER_02]: Without perspective, without yoniso.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It won't be concurrent attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if you're steadied in it, and, obviously, sense restraint and a correct mode of behavior would be supporting that practice of putting things in brackets, or step back.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And allowing it to endure from what you step back.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not fix, change, psychologize, modify, cover up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, yes, you would be, obviously, discerning more and more.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, you can you can learn
[SPEAKER_02]: how to now put these more refined aspects into brackets, because they are real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why I keep saying whatever, you know, like, even if there's like some ambiguous sense feeling or something, oh, the degree of its ambiguity, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: It does not require clarification in terms of
[SPEAKER_02]: Making it into something more palpable.
[SPEAKER_02]: You realize clarification is on the level of not ignoring even unclear things.
[SPEAKER_02]: This phenomenon is unclear.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's quite clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by regarding things this way, man cannot root out doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the mundane right view developed like this.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like pretty much paired with sense restraint and everything else would have to result into the right way of practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's what's lacking.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is instruction.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are people that practice restraint and keep the precepts and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there are not many people that know how to see things to the extent that they have arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are not many people that know that they have to change their attitude and recognize things existing as phenomena independent of their sense of their body and their mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Both.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just they are given first beforehand.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you realize, oh, this is first.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever's manifested, to the extent it's manifested, is the experience as a whole, is the totality of the experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any notion I have in regard to it, that's second.
[SPEAKER_02]: I am, identity, everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in order for that to be set into that right order, yeah, that attitude of yoniso, manasikāra, needs to be, like, needs to have been thoroughly developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, so it needs to become on the basic mode of attending.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Outside of the precepts, the restraint, would you say also
[SPEAKER_03]: I think you said it in one of the talks, just questioning yourself, like, who am I?
[SPEAKER_03]: Type of, like, questioning.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is this?
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the...?
[SPEAKER_03]: The meaning of this automatically forces you to head that direction, so to speak, like questioning...
[SPEAKER_02]: I wouldn't say automatically, because it would force probably you, because all of the other things you know about it, and what you should need, what you need to be looking for.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then it could probably result in that way.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you just say to somebody, just question yourself, it would sooner or later become mechanical.
[SPEAKER_02]: Questions and... or mystical.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just put yourself in a question and whatever experience comes out of it, and then the first thing that happens that's out of the ordinary will be the answer, whatever it might be.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yes, in principle, yes, the attitude of questioning is the attitude of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you develop satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you develop sati, through constant questioning and recollection.
[SPEAKER_02]: What am I doing?
[SPEAKER_02]: Why am I doing it?
[SPEAKER_02]: What's my...?"
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, all of these questions, just to, again, shed light back onto the wider situation, so that you unabsorb yourself from whatever you ended up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because nature, the nature of the sense organs, and you might just to fall into that focus, that means going with the grain.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, focusing, being absorbed, that's just following the grain.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you want to basically go against that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't just willingly unfocus, because that will become the object of your focus, new focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then you realize, oh, but while you focus, you can learn to see that's the peripheral and that whole thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, unfocus to the extent of whatever you've been focused at, without denying it, without trying to replace it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what's meant by, like, a reference point in satipaṭṭhāna, the practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the whole thing of concurrent is the while.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if... And that's why I'm stressing the concurrency of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if I'm just unfocusing from this, without concurrently knowing that what I'm focusing is still there, I would just be replacing one focus... one thing I'm focused on with another thing I'm focused on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're still freeing your mind a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Direction is not changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not going against the grain.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're just changing the object of your focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you do it concurrently, you realize it's not about changing the object.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's about discerning that peripheral to the object.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's about learning how to put it in the brackets while it is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: To see it to its own extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: To see this phenomena independent of, as I said, the world, the space, the time, in that sense, the body, the I am, any notions, any concepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, this is first introduced there on its own to the way it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when you get used to that, that's... by the way, that's where the work starts.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not what it ends.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, the way it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: I saw things the way they are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what are you doing now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you practicing what you think?
[SPEAKER_02]: You're enlightened.
[SPEAKER_02]: A thousand times more.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, you do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, to discern the properties of that phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why dhamma, the dhamma, is based on the word dhamma, which means things.
[SPEAKER_02]: The nature of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, the the mental objects are dhammas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what dhammas are.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize, yeah, everything is a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: Physical phenomenon, mental phenomenon, everything has that aspect of an image, of an enduring image, phenomenal image, so to speak, phenomenological image.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, understanding the characteristics of that, the nature of manifestation, the nature of anicca, dukkha, everything else in regard to its properties, oh, that's the way out, that's the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yoniso, manasikāra,
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you having dhammas available to be seen as dhammas, having discerned that, and the occurrence of another right instruction pointing certain things among those dhammas that you see now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, you have the right view, because you have a basis for it, and you have the instruction as to what to see.
[SPEAKER_04]: I find it difficult to regard the negative as a real thing, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, anything less present or anything that's less in the center of your perception...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: The attitude is a sort of attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: The word's attitude is, oh, this is less real.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's exactly what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Learning how to see things to the extent they are real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: Less real than what?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can actually question yourself in this regard.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, you recognize, oh my God, this is less real.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't just, will you see, oh, I'll stop doing this.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a result of wrongly attending to things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now that you spotted it,
[SPEAKER_02]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_02]: Reflect on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why does this feel less real?
[SPEAKER_02]: Less real to what?
[SPEAKER_02]: But if it's less real, how can I talk about it in this real sense?
[SPEAKER_02]: What am I thinking about?
[SPEAKER_02]: All these thoughts are pretty real.
[SPEAKER_02]: Feelings are pretty real.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, less real becomes real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: The attitude of less real is not something you need to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to see that as a real phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you stop regarding things as less real.
[SPEAKER_04]: I think what I'm bumping into is maybe more along the lines of, you know, there's thought of the origin, but is that the origin that I need to be aware of?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or is there something I need to search for?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, like, again, see, now, that question implies that the origin is outside of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you're seeking this origin from where everything comes from.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to see the origin as an object, and that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not the origin, even if it were the origin, because you're attending to it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there's no origin there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not like I have to stop that thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to see it real as such, and that's the origin.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, origin is when you don't overshoot or undershoot.
[SPEAKER_02]: Origin is when you attend to it rightly in the middle, or where it is, hence the middle way.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's where the origin is.
[SPEAKER_02]: You overshoot it, it's another object.
[SPEAKER_02]: Of your focus, of your attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: You understand?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's another object.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you find the origin not by... well, you attend with the origin.
[SPEAKER_02]: You learn how to attend concurrently.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not before or after.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, concurrent attention is what the yoniso manasikāra is for you at the time, even if you don't think that's what the yoniso manasikāra is.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it needs repetition and training.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not just an intellectual answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was going to say, practically speaking, you're probably going to have to do the... where you get sucked in, and then you step back out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Get sucked in.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: That you need that pushing back.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why the precepts and guiding of the sense door is everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just... it's there like a container, a gate that keeps you from, like, when you're sucked in, from, like, going too far.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's never optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body isn't there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within a feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those understandings, those clarities, would realize, oh, whether actually I tend to describe it or not, body is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Always does itself, always.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where you can become less involved, so to speak, with seeing things as phenomena and learning how to think rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, knowledge is taking over.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, mindfulness is resulting in certain perceptions becoming set now.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if... That's how Sotāpanna can become careless and can proliferate his sensuality and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But he cannot not see things as phenomena, fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_02]: That... he cannot go beyond... below anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's meant he can't take any saṅkhara as permanent or as pleasurable.
[SPEAKER_02]: If he sees... when he discerns things... when he doesn't ignore things on the level of an enduring phenomenon, eh... saṅkharas, dhammas, will not... cannot be taken itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: He cannot go past that... below that threshold again.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, to understand and practice
[SPEAKER_01]: yoniso, manasikāra, is necessary if a noble disciple is going to develop satipaṭṭhāna, because those four satipaṭṭhāna almost substitute the whole principle of the origin, knowing the concurrent attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: This, this is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, realizing that that origin is
[SPEAKER_01]: Already there, always, anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: You now realize what is always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling there, mind there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's only the origin as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the same applies to the origin.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's how it starts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not having understood that, one can then turn to the satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's bound to be going wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing to acquire.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the entire practitioner, the entire practice of dhamma is within the principle of kīyānussamānasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the whole thing, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yet, it's taught as carefully attending to something, or... Yeah, yeah, but... Appropriately attending...
[SPEAKER_02]: Wisely...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, none of that is necessarily wrong, etymologically, but it's like, well, but what does that mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: What does appropriately mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: What does wisely mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever feels right to a puṭṭhujana means it's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm making the effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's an absolute fundamental factor.
[SPEAKER_02]: The oneness with God, the utterance of another, gives rise to the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thus, if somebody who is practicing dhamma does not have the right view, well, it's only because these two factors are lacking, or one of them.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot be a third option.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot be...
[SPEAKER_02]: I have both factors, but I'm still not Sādhāpanna.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in Sādhāpanna, I'm going to say, this is wise, I think.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But we're talking about how to translate it, and then you realize, well, whichever way
[SPEAKER_02]: You will have to qualify it because it's it's not and it's not it's not on the level of an answer to what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the level of something that needs to be done and repeated and attitude needs to be reshaped towards your own experience, towards phenomena.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, for that, you're going to need a lot more description than just finding a perfect etymological match or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you say to a sotāpanna, attend appropriately or attend wisely...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the main problem, when people were referring to it with, like, as wise attention and so on, the main problem I kind of detected was, it was becoming something that anybody can do on the level of psychologization.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I just need to wisely go through the motions of telling myself all this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eh, this is good, and I do this, and I do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Remind myself and go through the recitations and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's my yoniso manasikāra practice.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a single factor whereby
[SPEAKER_02]: Right attitude makes sensuality disappear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wrongly attending to it makes it increase.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether you talk about it or not, whether you have secondary thoughts and plans and scenarios to scare you or whatever, just to put you off, oh, that's way too far down the line to proliferate.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's way on the level of sense objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words, you don't want to manage it, you want to approach it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Attention is basically gives rise to all things, how the Dānasūtra says.
[SPEAKER_02]: The womb of it, there is no deeper than that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, just to connect this with the side of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: It seems like they're very closely intertwined.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, putujana, developing yoniso manasikāra on the basis of sense restraint, guarding of the sense doors, seclusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said, seeing anything that manifests, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's right in front of you, or at the back of your mind, if it's subtle or coarse, big or small, ambiguous or clear, personal or impersonal, you see it arisen as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's exactly how you can get to spot the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because mind is a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a background of your mind, basically, what the mind is.
[SPEAKER_02]: The background of you currently, whatever absorbed experience you are, that ambiguous, kind of wide, non-specific sense, where your I am lingers, so to speak, that's the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not about investigating it, defining it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's about seeing it as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the signs of the mind, not the signs that I put in the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's that's exactly going to be the result of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why sign of the mind needs to be seen before the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said, yonisonma-sikāra is developing the right attitude, the correct attitude towards any phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, once, if you don't see the phenomenon of the mind or mind as phenomenon, as an enduring thing there in the background, how can you develop your attitude towards it?
[SPEAKER_02]: How can you train it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why it's necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sign of the mind is necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: What would I say now?
[SPEAKER_02]: That somebody can become accomplished in the right view, having not grasped the signs of the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Such thing is not possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, sign of the mind only reveals itself in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: In seclusion, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, he does not delay.
[SPEAKER_02]: He doesn't go to sleep.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you could describe, like, the sign of the mind as point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, practically, on a day-to-day basis, there is a sense of the direction of your view, the point of view.
[SPEAKER_02]: from where you're attending.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just never... Again, it's less real.
[SPEAKER_02]: It feels like it's less real than everything else that you are attending.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why one is attending lustful things, one is attending... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: ...aversive things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if... even if one stops attending that, sure, you step back to a degree.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, if you don't go into seclusion,
[SPEAKER_02]: That point of view will still feel like less real.
[SPEAKER_02]: Less palpable, thus means less real.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you don't say, I don't think it means less real for me, you imply that it's less real by being unclear about its extent of its phenomenology.
[SPEAKER_04]: So when I think people have a conversation with the Buddha in suttas, and they attain stream entry right there and then,
[SPEAKER_04]: Does that sort of just imply that before meeting him, they were already...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, the Buddha would have... when he said there are two factors for the stream entry, yoniso manasikāra and attidance of anāgāra, if those were not the only factors, he would have said, oh, there is yoniso manasikāra and attidance of anāgāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, another factor for the right view is just being lucky to talk to him.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: He didn't say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether you talk to the Buddha, whether he's the one giving the right instruction, sure, he'll be the most accurate.
[SPEAKER_02]: He'll know exactly what you need to hear.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if you haven't met him halfway, in other words, if you don't have yonisonāmasikāra, he can be talking all he wants.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't understand.
[SPEAKER_03]: As it happened with people.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, he was actually instructing them for the right view, and they didn't get it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they haven't... they were not authentic.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were not authentic, because they were not restrained.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were not restrained, because they were behaving unwholesomely and not keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it's covering it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mind's aimed by ignorance, which then prevents the right view from dawning, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Talking about the, like, existentialists and the phenomenologists.
[SPEAKER_04]: What is the...
[SPEAKER_04]: Distinction between a patujana whose authenticity drives him crazy, like Nietzsche, for example, and the one who, you know, becomes, you know, starts dwelling in the jhānas, you know, he's a
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can sort of develop
[SPEAKER_04]: A degree of authenticity without... Yeah, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some people, obviously, are, you know, their faculties are sharper, minds quicker, they can see through stuff, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like the different types of persons that everybody's talking about in the service.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some can just practice with very little instruction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some can need a bit more.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have everything right, but still won't go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: We'll just hope that's done.
[SPEAKER_02]: For the fact that somebody already can recognize the value of dhamma, has the inspiration to practice means that we're far from hopeless.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, yeah, how much of that suffering and anxiety we probably have to endure?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that depends on
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the right tapas that you would inspire.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you can repress pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can seem very restrained, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's what I said.
[SPEAKER_02]: Precepts and so on will not automatically result in yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: Inauthenticity, unknowing, incognito, things like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think we talked about this too, Upādānante, Pāssanāpāyana.
[SPEAKER_03]: There isn't anything that really happens when you do attend from the origin.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, there's no change in front.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, there's nothing...
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why people want to really recognize the value of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are no players and fantasies.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, there is no novelty to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I was saying that before, I gave that similar, like, you know, waiting for a bus, but there's no bus stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's like, unless you know where you just, kind of, keep yourself, kind of, okay, I'll stay within this range, you won't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's nothing else telling you, pointing you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you do need to learn and then keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why, as I said many times, right view cannot be obtained by accident or magically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because who will by accident stay, practice that which has no immediate palpable verification and confirmation?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, this is why also this one sutta says that it's independent of faith that I should be so manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you will not have immediate fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, sorry, what it says?
[SPEAKER_02]: That it's all based on faith.
[SPEAKER_02]: You want to be so manasikāra?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, wow.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, there you go.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't need to tell you, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which sutta is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in the Gutturamika, in the book of the tenths.
[SPEAKER_02]: But can you send me the actual instructions?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, no, that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to have a degree
[SPEAKER_02]: Because everything else, you want to make it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Make it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get the sensations.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get the overwhelming experience of meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get the inspiration.
[SPEAKER_02]: Get something that you can squeeze, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: Something that you can see, perceive, in that direct sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, unless you have faith, to ignore that thought, to not give in to that everything's haunting, but you want to feel so real, and stay with this that doesn't feel quite real,
[SPEAKER_02]: Repeatedly endure the pain on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Most people would probably have to today.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, yeah, without faith you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means without faith you won't get the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's difficult to recognize, because, in a sense, there's no north to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, when discussing it, somebody might actually recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, they don't need to face the state of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's still going nowhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as I said, like, it's like, you know, you need to repeat it so many times.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, cultivate dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to cultivate the attitude, so it grows and spreads and becomes more firm.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why it's like, not on the level of answers and kind of...
[SPEAKER_02]: Satisfactory, pleasing, figuring out of the ideas.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's... that can contribute, if you figure out the right ideas, but you mustn't ignore the fact, okay, but now I should actually start doing this, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Concurrently attending to whatever's... whatever's presently have taken the focus already, and then not finding specific objects to be attended or focused on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, less real.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that that really sums it up for most people.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that's exactly the main, the core of the Kutujana's problem and lack, to be honest, of nāmasikāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't recognize that things that are less real are real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they keep maintaining the threshold, the measure of what feels real for them, what feels really real.
[SPEAKER_02]: They measure things against that, you know, failing to understand that, well, something less real is still real as such.
[SPEAKER_03]: You find it difficult.
[SPEAKER_03]: It kind of indicates that it's real.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: How could you talk about it?
[SPEAKER_03]: It would not be manifested in which this is not real.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's a repeated recognition of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: If less real things are real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not real as much, but real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: As such.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the standard you use for determining what is real, I guess that is why central strength comes to make that standard.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly why, if right view is developed, you will overcome doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the core, the source of power that dharma has, it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seeking what's real and palpable as the answer and refusing to accept the lack of clarity, ambiguity.
[SPEAKER_02]: It pressures you and you automatically have to get rid of that pressure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, see, less real means, well, less mind, less in my control.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's confirming me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, ātavāda, doubt, go hand-in-hand to that level, that extent.
[SPEAKER_02]: And withdrawal from the putting the world and the sense of duty to avoid the pressure of real or less real and doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sīla Bhāgavatamās, the first three fetches.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can see why they would come.
[SPEAKER_02]: It makes sense even now, when I'm discovering why exactly they would be the first three fetches to come off with development, to be honest, when I'm discovering the right construction.